<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic xmlns:ditaarch="http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/" id="Creating-Serna-GUI-Translations-Internationalization-i18n">
  <title>Creating Serna GUI Translations ( Internationalization, i18n)</title>
  <body>
    <section>
      <p>Serna user interface language can be changed.  For internationalization Serna uses binary files located in $SERNA_DATA_DIR/translations folder. The naming convention for such files is <codeph>serna_LANG_ID.qm</codeph> where <codeph> LANG_ID </codeph> is language identifier and defines the language of the translation file.</p>
      <note>
        <p><codeph> LANG_ID </codeph> is an arbitrary string but  it&apos;s recommended to make language IDs in accordance with the rules outlined in RFC 3066.</p>
      </note>
      <p>If you need to create a new GUI translation for the Serna application, please contact Syntext and get Serna application translation templates (this is free). Put these files into the  $SERNA_DATA_DIR/translations directory. These files contain translatable strings that are used to produce binary translation files, and have the names in form XXXX_untranslated.ts, where XXXX corresponds to the different application module names:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>serna_untranslated.ts</b>
          <p>Translation template for Serna application.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>qt_untranslated.ts</b>
          <p>Translation template for Qt GUI library.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>qscintilla_untranslated.ts</b>
          <p>Translation template for QScintilla widget which is used for Serna plain text editor.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>You must translate all these templates if you want to get a fully localized application. However, in many cases translation of serna_untranslated.ts  may be  enough.</p>
      <p>For example, to translate &apos;<codeph>serna</codeph>&apos; module  you should make the following steps:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>In $SERNA_DATA_DIR/translations copy serna_untranslated.ts to <codeph>serna_LANG_ID.ts</codeph> (For example <codeph>&quot;serna_fi.ts&quot;</codeph> for Finnish).</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>In SERNA_INSTALLATION_PATH/bin  folder  run linguist tool.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>In the main menu choose File-&gt;Open and open  serna_LANG_ID.ts file.</p>
          <image href="linguist.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>For each context in the left pane translate all source texts and mark them as done.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Save the translation file.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>In main menu use File-&gt;Release... to produce serna_LANG_ID.qm  binary file. Ensure that binary file is located in $SERNA_DATA_DIR/translations directory.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Switch to newly supported language via <menucascade>
              <uicontrol>Preferences</uicontrol>
            </menucascade> dialog.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
