<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic xmlns:ditaarch="http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/" id="using-serna-for-metadata">
  <title>Using Serna PIs for Associating XML Metadata with Documents</title>
  <body>
    <section>
      <p>Each XML document requires certain metadata for  the editing process, such as  a stylesheet and XML schema. There  are three ways to specify document metadata: manually, from  the Advanced tab in  the Open File or New Document dialogs, via the document template, and via Serna processing instructions (PIs), specified in the prolog of the document. Of these, manually specified parameters have the highest precedence,  followed by parameters specified in PIs, then template-specified parameters. </p>
      <p>Serna PIs always have the form:<codeblock>&lt;?syntext-serna param=&quot;value&quot; ...?&gt;</codeblock>An arbitrary number of parameters can be specified in a single <codeph>syntext-serna</codeph> PI.</p>
      <note type="important">
        <p>Serna PIs must be specified <b>BEFORE</b> prolog&apos;s and document elements. If these PIs are specified anywhere else, they will be ignored.</p>
      </note>
      <note type="important">
        <p>These PIs will not take effect if added to  an already open document. Reload  the document if you added the PI in Serna text mode.</p>
      </note>
      <p>The following parameters are available:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>xml-stylesheet</b>
          <p>Specifies path to Serna XSL stylesheet for this document. If stylesheet path is relative, it is resolved relative to the document URI. Note that Serna ignores  the <codeph>&lt;?xml-stylesheet href=&quot;path&quot;?&gt;</codeph> PI because it is often oversubscribed and used by other applications.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>xml-schema</b>
          <p>Specifies XML schema for this document. If  the path to the XML schema is relative, it is resolved relative to the document URI.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>last-position</b>
          <p>Specifies position where cursor should stand when this document is opened. This PI is automatically generated by Serna when document is saved.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
