<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="getting-started" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:oasis:names:tc:dita:xsd:topic.xsd:1.1">
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <body>
    <p><ul>
        <li>
          <p><b>What Serna Is</b></p>
          <p><term>Syntext Serna</term><indexterm>Syntext Serna</indexterm> is a WYSIWYG XML editor, almost like a conventional word processor. Serna is designed for <xref href="wysiwyg-mode-serna-free.xml">WYSIWYG document presentation</xref>: XML documents can be viewed in print-like appearance without even XML markup tags, if you wish.</p>
          <p>In <xref href="wysiwyg-mode-serna-free.xml">WYSIWYG mode</xref>, you are free to change the document tree under the root element. Besides, you can  change and remove entity declarations. So when you find yourself desiring to switch to  <xref href="markup-in-editing-window-serna-free.xml">XML markup mode</xref> or to <xref href="plain-text-mode-serna-free.xml">Text mode</xref> (pure XML code mode), please be aware that there should be an easy way of handling the same use-case in  <xref href="wysiwyg-mode-serna-free.xml">WYSIWYG mode</xref>. However, you can use <xref href="plain-text-mode-serna-free.xml">Text mode</xref> for specific cases like changing the DOCTYPE declaration or the root element of a document, which is not allowed in <xref href="wysiwyg-mode-serna-free.xml">WYSIWYG mode</xref>.  </p>
          <p>Every document opened or created  in Serna is associated with a particular <xref href="document-type.xml">document type</xref>.  Depending on the <xref href="document-type.xml">document type</xref> and the <xref href="authoring-modes-serna-free.xml">authoring mode</xref>, you get a particular <xref href="serna-gui-serna-free.xml">graphical user interface of Serna</xref> and <xref href="content-rendering-serna-free.xml">the view of the document</xref> in the Editing Window. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><b>What Serna Is Not</b></p>
          <p>Serna is not  an XML development environment. You will not find it convenient for coding, say, XSL stylesheets or XML schemas. The nice appearance of XML documents like DITA, Docbook and TEI is exactly what Serna is designed for.</p>
        </li>
      </ul></p>
  </body>
</topic>
