<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN" "task.dtd" []>
<task xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="inserting-reference-to-newly-created-document-in-dita-map" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:oasis:names:tc:dita:xsd:task.xsd:1.1">
  <title>Inserting Reference to Newly-Created Document in DITA Map</title>
  <taskbody>
    <context>
      <p>To insert a reference to a newly-created document, do the following</p>
    </context>
    <steps>
      <step>
        <cmd>In DITA Map, place the cursor where to insert the topicref.</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Call up the <uicontrol>Insert New DITA Document Reference Dialog</uicontrol>.</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>To call up the <keyword>Insert New DITA Document Reference Dialog</keyword>, choose <menucascade>
              <uicontrol>DITA</uicontrol>
              <uicontrol>Insert New DITA Document Reference</uicontrol>
            </menucascade> or click the <uicontrol>Insert New DITA Document Reference</uicontrol> button <image href="insert-new-dita-document-reference-button.png" align="center"/> on the toolbar.</p>
        </info>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Specify parameters for the new document.</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>In the<uicontrol> Insert New DITA Document Reference Dialog</uicontrol>, do the following:</p>
        </info>
        <substeps>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Specify the document template.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>From the <uicontrol>Template</uicontrol> drop-down list, select a template for the new document.</p>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Specify the title.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>In the <uicontrol>Title</uicontrol> field, type the title of the new document.</p>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Specify the ID.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>The <uicontrol>Id</uicontrol> field gets filled in automatically when you are typing the title.</p>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Specify the filename.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>In the <uicontrol>File</uicontrol> field, specify the name of the new document.</p>
              <p><note>
                  <p>The new document will be saved in the directory of the current document. To specify another location for saving the new document, use the <uicontrol>Browse</uicontrol> button.</p>
                </note></p>
            </info>
          </substep>
        </substeps>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Make the newly-created document open upon the topicref insertion.</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>Check the <uicontrol>Open after insert</uicontrol> checkbox to open the newly-created document upon the topicref insertion.</p>
        </info>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Insert the topicref.</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>Click the <uicontrol>Insert</uicontrol> button to insert the topicref.</p>
          <image href="insert-new-dita-document-reference-dialog.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
        </info>
        <stepresult>
          <p>The new document will be created and the topicref will be inserted.</p>
        </stepresult>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </taskbody>
</task>
