<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd" []>
<concept xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="paginated-and-normal-document-views" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:oasis:names:tc:dita:xsd:concept.xsd:1.1">
  <title>Paginated and Normal Document Views</title>
  <conbody>
    <p>Documents opened in the <xref href="wysiwyg-mode-serna-free.xml"/> can have two views  in the <xref href="editing-window-serna-free.xml"/>:<ol>
        <li>
          <p><b>Paginated view.</b></p>
          <p>In the Paginated view, the content of a document is divided into multiple numbered pages.  The page size is governed by the <xref href="xsl-stylesheet.xml"/>. This view is convenient when working with extensive documents such as Docbook.</p>
          <fig>
            <title> Paginated view of a document.</title>
            <image href="paginated-view.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
          </fig>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><b>Normal view.</b></p>
          <p>In the Normal view, the content of the whole document is displayed on a single page. This view is  convenient when you prefer to avoid breaks in content, for example when you work with tables. Also, when you deal with DITA documents, pagination is unnecessary.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>Normal view of a document.</title>
            <image href="normal-view.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
          </fig>
        </li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>By default, Docbook documents are opened paginated, and DITA documents are opened as a single page. You can configure what  view should be default for a particular <xref href="document-type.xml">document type</xref>. For instructions, see <xref href="specifying-default-document-view-serna-free.xml"/>.</p>
    <p>To switch between the Paginated view and the Normal view when working with a document, choose <menucascade>
        <uicontrol>View</uicontrol>
        <uicontrol>Show Paginated View/Show Normal View</uicontrol>
      </menucascade> or click the <uicontrol>Show Paginated View/Show Normal View</uicontrol> button <image href="paginated-normal-view-button.png" align="center"/> on the <xref href="status-bar-serna-free.xml">Status bar</xref>. </p>
    <p><note>
        <p>To be <xref href="printing-draft-serna-free.xml">printed as draft</xref> from Serna, a document must be paginated. Otherwise, on attempting to print a document displayed as a single page, the dialog prompting you to switch to the paginated view will appear.<image href="document-cannot-be-printed-in-normal-view-message.png" align="center" placement="break"/></p>
      </note></p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
