<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd" []>
<concept xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="ssl-support" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:oasis:names:tc:dita:xsd:concept.xsd:1.1">
  <title>SSL Support</title>
  <conbody>
    <p>The Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) protocol provides for secure communication between Serna and a remote HTTP or WebDAV server.</p>
    <p>Serna initiates SSL connection on HTTP/WebDAV requests to a remote server using the HTTPS protocol (<filepath>https://</filepath>).</p>
    <p>When you try to <xref href="open-doc-webdav.xml">open</xref> a secure document from an HTTP/WebDAV server, the server sends its certificate. Serna SSL client plugin checks that:<ol>
        <li>
          <p><b>The server certificate was issued by a trusted party.</b></p>
          <p>The incoming server certificate must be signed by one of your <xref href="managing-ca-certificates.xml">CA certificates</xref>. Otherwise, the connection will be rejected and the <uicontrol>Server Certified by an Unknown Authority</uicontrol> message will appear.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>Server Certified by an Unknown Authority message.</title>
            <image href="server-certified-by-an-unknown-authority-message.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
          </fig>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><b>The server certificate is valid.</b></p>
          <p>The incoming server certificate must be valid. Otherwise, the connection will be rejected and the <uicontrol>Server Certificate Expired</uicontrol> message or the <uicontrol>Server Certificate Not Yet Valid</uicontrol> message will appear.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>Server Certificate Expired message.</title>
            <image href="server-certificate-expired-message.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
          </fig>
          <p id="view-certificate">To view the server certificate, click the <uicontrol>View Certificate</uicontrol> button.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><b>The server certificate is related to the site contacted.</b></p>
          <p>The hostname for which the incoming server certificate was issued must match the entered hostname of the server. Otherwise, the connection will be rejected and the <uicontrol>Security Error: Domain Name Mismatch</uicontrol> message will appear.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>Security Error: Domain Name Mismatch message.</title>
            <image href="security-error-domain-name-mismatch-message.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
          </fig>
          <p conref="#ssl-support/view-certificate"/>
        </li>
      </ol></p>
    <p><note>
        <p>You can <xref href="webdav-properties.xml">force the connection with untrusted servers</xref>. In this case, SSL warnings will be shown just once,  and Serna will continue establishing the connection.</p>
      </note></p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
