<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN" "task.dtd" []>
<task xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="using-element-help" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:oasis:names:tc:dita:xsd:task.xsd:1.1">
  <title>Using <?serna-redline-start 0 this topic should be divided into
- element help
- attribute help?>Element Help<?serna-redline-end?></title>
  <taskbody>
    <context>
      <p>Serna includes the  ability to display help information for elements and attributes for the current <xref href="xml-schema.xml">Schema</xref>.</p>
      <p>DITA Element Help comes with Serna distribution. You can also <xref href="http://www.syntext.com/downloads/index.htm" format="html">download Docbook Element Help</xref>.<note>
          <p>If you would like to create Element Help for your own document type (XML schema),  see Developer&apos;s Guide, <xref href="../developers_guide/element-help-definition.xml"/>. To enable element help, the path to the element help file must be specified in a <xref href="serna-document-template.xml">document template</xref> . For more details about document templates and element help file format, see Developer&apos;s Guide, <xref href="../developers_guide/creating-element-help.xml"/>.</p>
        </note></p>
      <p>When Serna Element Help is enabled, it can be invoked  several ways:</p>
    </context>
    <steps>
      <step>
        <cmd>Call up Element Help for the element at the cursor position.</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>To call up the full help page for the element at the current cursor position in the document, do one of the following:</p>
        </info>
        <choices>
          <choice>
            <p>Choose  <menucascade>
                <uicontrol>Help</uicontrol>
                <uicontrol>Element Help</uicontrol>
              </menucascade>.</p>
          </choice>
          <choice>
            <p>Press <uicontrol>F11</uicontrol>.</p>
          </choice>
          <choice>
            <p>Press the <uicontrol>Help for the Current Element</uicontrol>  button <image href="element-help-button.png" align="center"/> on the toolbar.</p>
          </choice>
        </choices>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Call up Element Help from the <keyword>Insert Element Dialog</keyword>.</cmd>
        <substeps>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Call up a tooltip with short help.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>To call up a tooltip with short help for an element, move the mouse pointer over the element in the <keyword>Insert Element Dialog</keyword>. </p>
              <image href="element-hint.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Call up the full help page.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>To call up the full help page for an element, select the element in the <keyword>Insert Element Dialog</keyword> and click the <uicontrol>Help for the Current Element</uicontrol>  button <image href="element-help-button.png" align="center"/>.</p>
            </info>
          </substep>
        </substeps>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Call up Attributes Help from the <keyword>Attributes Dialog</keyword>.</cmd>
        <substeps>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Call up a tooltip with short help.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>To call up a tooltip with short help for an attribute, move the mouse pointer over the attribute&apos;s cell in the <keyword>Attributes Dialog</keyword>, or over the attribute in a combo-box.</p>
              <image href="tooltip-in-attributes-dialog.png" align="center" placement="break"/>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Call up the full help page.</cmd>
            <info>
              <p>To call up the full help page for an attribute, select the attribute in the <keyword>Attributes Dialog</keyword> and click the <uicontrol>Help for Current Attribute</uicontrol>  button <image href="element-help-button.png" align="center"/>.</p>
            </info>
          </substep>
        </substeps>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </taskbody>
</task>
