<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd" []>
<concept xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="xsl-stylesheet" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:oasis:names:tc:dita:xsd:concept.xsd:1.1">
  <title>XSL Stylesheet</title>
  <conbody id="body">
<?serna-redline-start 0 may be structured better
why XSL used?
what the benefits? (profiling, localizaiton, composition, etc)?>    <p>XSL stylesheet  prescribes how to render a document in WYSIWYG Mode.</p>
    <p>Serna comes with stylesheets for supported popular <xref href="document-type.xml">document types</xref>, e.g. <xref href="docbook-stylesheet.xml">Docbook stylesheet</xref>, DITA stylesheets, TEI stylesheet, etc. You can also <xref href="../developers_guide/xsl-stylesheet-development.xml">develop your own stylesheets</xref>. Usually it&apos;s better to    have a specific stylesheet for your <xref href="document-type.xml">document type</xref>, but you can use the generic <xref href="default-stylesheet.xml">
        <keyword>default stylesheet</keyword>
      </xref>, if you do not have a specific one.</p>
    <p>DITA and Docbook stylesheets come with localizations so that you can <xref href="localization-in-stylesheets.xml">change the language of the element content</xref>.</p>
    <p>In Serna, when you <xref href="creating-new-document.xml">create a new document with a Serna document template</xref>, a corresponding stylesheet prescribed by the template is applied automatically. You can also assign the path to some stylesheet other than that prescribed by the selected template.</p>
    <p>When you <xref href="opening-a-document-in-wysiwyg-mode.xml">open a document</xref>, a corresponding stylesheet is  applied automatically by means of a <xref href="serna-document-template.xml">Serna document template</xref> that matches the document. You can also <xref href="opening-document-with-manually-specified-parameters.xml">open a document with some other template that prescribes another stylesheet</xref>.  </p>
    <p>You can <xref href="viewing-document-properties.xml">see what XSL Stylesheet is currently applied to your document</xref>.</p>
<?serna-redline-end?>  </conbody>
</concept>
